<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<root>
    <note
        source="https://americanwomeninwwi.wordpress.com/2017/06/26/marian-baldwin-canteen-worker/"
        >All letters in this collection are by Marian Baldwin (1895-1972). <md
            source="https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/186043073/marian-steiner">She was 22 at the
            time these letters were written</md>.</note>
    <letter n="1">
        <subject>Letter from <person>Marian Baldwin</person>, <date><month>June</month> 30,
                    <year>1917</year></date></subject>

        <heading>
            <para>On Board <obj foreignLanguage="French" objType="boat">La Touraine</obj>,</para>

            <para>
                <date><month>June</month> 30th, <year>1917</year></date>.</para>
        </heading>

        <para>Even now that we are out of sight of land, it seems impossible that I am actually off
            to <loc geo="country">France</loc> and, for the first time in my life, traveling alone.
            Everything has happened so quickly since the <org note="aka A.F.F.W">American Fund for
                French Wounded</org> found an opening for me in <loc geo="city">Paris</loc> that I
            suppose I am still somewhat dazed and bewildered. The fact that I don't know what it
            will all be like and that I can't look ahead makes it easier to be happy and live in the
            present. Of course I have had a bit of a taste in <loc geo="city">New York</loc> of the
            work that the <org note="American Fund for French Wounded">A. F. F. W.</org> is doing
            but its Headquarters in <loc geo="city">Paris</loc> will be different in some ways I
            fancy.</para>

        <para>I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how few girls of my
                <context note="22">age</context> are getting across, and I understood the grit and
            pluck which made you encourage me on my great adventure and send me along a path which
            has proved so dangerous of late.</para>

        <para>As we drifted down <loc geo="water">the river</loc>, in the sunset glow with two
            absurd <obj objType="boat">tugs</obj> puffing alongside, I know that many eyes were
            moist and that the same thought was in all our minds. How many of this ship's company
            will see that sky-line again! It was very quiet, no one spoke much, and, little by
            little, the glow faded from the sky and one star after another appeared. I knew that you
            would be looking at those same stars down in <loc geo="city" note="Lakewood, NJ"
                >Lakewood</loc> and that your thoughts and prayers were the same that filled my
            heart at that moment. Somehow distance does not separate, after all.</para>

        <para>We waited near the <obj objType="statue">Statue of Liberty</obj> until
                <time>midnight</time>—a rumor had it that a "personage" was to come on board. This
            individual was shrouded in mystery until we put to sea when it was given out that the
            party which had clambered aboard in the night was none other than the <org>Italian
                Mission</org>. Our spirits rose at once for, what with <person>Frank Sayre</person>
            on the boat and these distinguished Italian gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by
            a bigger convoy and so doubly safe. However, thus far we have but two <obj
                objType="boat">destroyer</obj>s following us. They can be seen distinctly outlined
            against the horizon, one on each side, and seem to be the same somber gray which all
            ships are affecting in <event note="WWI">this war</event> A sailor informed me this
            morning that we weren't in much danger for the first four or five days but that after
            that I might see some excitement. Here's hoping!</para>

        <para>I have a small inside cabin and my room-mate is quite a character. She is a native of
                <loc geo="country">Haiti</loc>, voluble and very portly — has four large pieces of
            baggage in our tiny stateroom, wears a costume which resembles a <note
                href="old-mother-hubbard-went-to-the-cupboard-to-get-her-poor-dog-a-bone-ce489c.jpg"
                >Mother Hubbard</note> and smokes countless thin cigarettes that smell like incense
            ! When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much room for me but, as she says, luckily I
            am small, and I was soon tucked into the upper berth with my belongings! She really
            isn't bad and after looking me over carefully told me that she didn't think we would
            fight and from that time has beamed upon me! She is going over to join her son who has
            been fighting with the French since the beginning of <event aka="WWI">the war</event>
            but will never go back to <loc>the Front</loc> now, having lost some fingers off each
            hand. She is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't lost more than his fingers.</para>

        <cite>Source: _Canteening Overseas_ 1917-1919, published 1920.</cite>
    </letter>
    <letter n="2">
        <heading>
            <date><month>July</month> 8th, <year>1917</year></date>
        </heading>
        <!-- tjv: I figured out the specific dates once MB established that July 8th was a Sunday. -->
        <para><note date="July 6">Friday night</note> we entered the war zone at <time>seven
                o'clock</time> but you would never know it. Aside from boat-drills and sleeping on
            deck people act as usual. The officers on <obj>the boat</obj> are very particular about
            the drills; several times the alarm has sounded and we have been taught just what to do
            in case we are hit. It's very funny to see the people rush below for their valuables,
            strapping on their life preservers as they go (which we always have near at hand
            wherever we are -on deck or in the saloon). In about five minutes we are lined up,
            divided into groups in front of our own particular life-boats which have been swung out
            over the sea ready to lower. Every one is checked off and each man is told what woman he
            is to save. (Great excitement at this point as no one of the men wants to save the lady
            detailed to him, but some one in another boat!) We all stand about looking too absurd
            and bumping into each other's life preservers on the crowded upper deck. Finally the
            signal is given which releases us, and we all file down again to take off the clumsy
            heavy jackets of safety and regale ourselves with various amusements on the deck.</para>

        <para>Rumor has it that two ships have been sunk, one in the course ahead of where we were
                <date aka="saturday, July 7">yesterday</date> and the other about an hour behind us.
            No one knows how many lives were lost. Perhaps those three <obj objType="boat"
                >submarines</obj> were more fact than fiction after all.</para>

        <para>It is thought that we should make <loc geo="city">Bordeaux</loc> by <date
                aka="July 10">Tuesday</date>
            <time>morning</time> if all goes well and that the <obj quantity="group" objType="boat"
                >convoy</obj> which should have met us <date aka="nonSpecific">days ago</date> will
            be with us <time>to-night</time>.</para>

        <para>This being Sunday, the boys on board are very much dressed up, that is to say they are
            wearing clean shirts and have their hair brushed! It's a perfect day, warm and
            cloudless, and I've been lying in the sun adding to my coat of tan. We all feel quite
            sad that the voyage is so nearly over -it has been such loads of fun and I shall hate
            saying good-by to every one.</para>

        <para>
            <obj foreignLanguage="French" objType="boat">La Touraine</obj>
        </para>
    </letter>
    <letter n="3">
        <heading>En route from <loc geo="city">Bordeaux</loc> to <loc geo="city">Paris</loc>,
                    <date><month>July</month> 18th, <year>1917</year></date>.</heading>


        <para>On landing yesterday I went straight to the <loc geo="building"
                foreignLanguage="French">Hôtel de France</loc> and it certainly was good to have
            room to turn around in: as for a bed with real springs I greeted it with enthusiasm!
            Towards <time>evening</time> Frank
            <!-- tjv: is she refering to Frank Sayre, I wonder? --> and I took a long walk about the
            city. A port town always interests me and we saw it all at the loveliest time of day.
            The harbor was full of fishing smacks and small craft of all kinds and exquisite tones
            in the sails and rigging. The last rays of the sun cast a rosy hue over everything,
            making one think at once of <loc geo="city">Venice</loc> and the days before <event
                aka="WWI">the war</event>. Later we wandered through some of the oldest parts of
                <loc geo="city">Bordeaux</loc> and I really felt that I was abroad again! The narrow
            winding streets and cobblestones, with here and there an ancient façade or doorway and
            everywhere, in the poorest alleys, a bit of a vine or potted plant in the windows. How
            do they manage to make it all so picturesque and alluring?</para>

        <para>The women and the old men are doing everything and it is surprising to see the lady
            conductors. On this <obj>train</obj> they use women entirely, even in the dining car.
            The war hasn't robbed them of vivacity or their beautiful complexions and I believe they
            are even prettier in their simple black working clothes than before.</para>

        <para>We are at present passing through the famous vineyards and I have never seen the
            country look so beautiful. The crops seem in perfect condition, thanks to the patient
            labor of these wonderful women, and the grain waves in profusion everywhere. I have
            longed for you at every turn, how you would enjoy it all. The poppies are in their prime
            and, as the train whirls by, they look like immense splashes of red -almost like stains
            of blood against the gold of the wheat.</para>

        <para>I have just come in from a very excellent meal in the dining car -the food was served
            promptly by two French girls of the peasant type and with a speed that was wonderful,
            the car holding over thirty persons.</para>

        <para>
            <loc geo="city">Paris</loc>
        </para>
    </letter>
</root>
